Shrevas Pai

Contact

E-mail: shreyas.pai@aalto.fi

INFORMATION Phone: +358 504737201 (M) +91 9833669064 (Whatsapp)

Website: https://shreyaspai.com

RESEARCH Interests My research interests are primarily in Theory of Distributed and Parallel Computing, more specifically in Distributed Graph Algorithms and Algorithms for Large Data. I am also more generally interested in topics in Theoretical Computer Science like Communication Complexity and Combinatorial Optimization.

Professional Experience

♦ Postdoctoral Researcher

**Aalto University*, Finland

Host: Jara Uitto.

Research Assistant Aug 2017 – May 2019

Aug 2021 – present

Aug 2016 - May 2021

The University of Iowa, USA Computational Epidemiology Group

EDUCATION

♦ PhD and MS in Computer Science
The University of Iowa, USA

Advisor: Sriram V. Pemmaraju. CGPA: 4.07/4

♦ B.Tech in Computer Engineering

Veermata Jijabai Technological Institute, India

Aug 2017 − May 2019

CGPA: 8.13/10

Manuscripts

- 1. Constant Time Parallel Almost Maximal Independent Set with Applications to Correlation Clustering and Ruling Sets, (under review) with Mélanie Cambus, Fabian Kuhn, Etna Lindy, and Jara Uitto.
- 2. Message Complexity of Distributed Approximation, (under review) with Fabien Dufoulon, Gopal Pandurangan, Sriram Pemmaraju, and Peter Robinson.
- 3. Fast Dynamic Programming in Trees in the MPC Model, (under review) with Chetan Gupta, Rustam Latypov, Yannic Maus, Simo Särkkä, Jan Studený, Jukka Suomela, Jara Uitto, and Hossein Vahidi.
- 4. Faster Set Cover in the MPC Model, with Hongyan Ji, Sriram Pemmaraju, and Joshua Sobel.

Conference Publications

1. Sinkless Orientation Made Simple

Alkida Balliu, Janne H. Korhonen, Fabian Kuhn, Henrik Lievonen, Dennis Olivetti, Shreyas Pai, Ami Paz, Joel Rybicki, Stefan Schmid, Jan Studený, Jukka Suomela, and Jara Uitto Symposium on Simplicity in Algorithms SOSA 2023 pp. 175–191

- 2. Brief Announcement: Distributed Reconfiguration of Spanning Trees
 Siddharth Gupta, Manish Kumar, and Shreyas Pai
 Stabilization, Safety, and Security of Distributed Systems, SSS 2022 pp. 346–351
- 3. Brief Announcement: Deterministic Massively Parallel Algorithms for Ruling Sets Shreyas Pai and Sriram V. Pemmaraju

 ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, PODC 2022 pp. 366–368

- $\begin{array}{l} 4.\ Risk-aware\ Temporal\ Cascade\ Reconstruction\ to\ Detect\ Asymptomatic\ Cases\ :\ For\ the\ CDC\\ MInD\ Healthcare\ Network \end{array}$
 - Hankyu Jang, Shreyas Pai, Bijaya Adhikari, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju *IEEE International Conference on Data Mining, ICDM* 2021 pp. 240–249
- 5. Can We Break Symmetry with o(m) Communication? Shreyas Pai, Gopal Pandurangan, Sriram V. Pemmaraju, and Peter Robinson ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, PODC 2021 pp. 247–257
- Sample-And-Gather: Fast Ruling Set Algorithms in the Low-Memory MPC Model
 Kishore Kothapalli, Shreyas Pai, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju
 IARCS Annual Conference on Foundations of Software Technology and Theoretical Computer
 Science, FSTTCS 2020 pp. 28:1–28:18
- Connectivity Lower Bounds in Broadcast Congested Clique
 Shreyas Pai and Sriram V. Pemmaraju
 IARCS Annual Conference on Foundations of Software Technology and Theoretical Computer Science, FSTTCS 2020 pp. 32:1–32:17
- 8. Distributed Approximation on Power Graphs
 Reuven Bar-Yehuda, Keren Censor-Hillel, Yannic Maus, Shreyas Pai, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju
 ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, PODC 2020 pp. 501–510
- Spatiotemporal clustering of in-hospital Clostridioides difficile infection
 Shreyas Pai, Philip M. Polgreen, Alberto Maria Segre, Daniel K. Sewell, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju
 Infection Control and Hospital Epidemiology 2020 pp. 418–424
- A Constant Approximation for Colorful k-Center
 Sayan Bandyapadhyay, Tanmay Inamdar, Shreyas Pai, and Kasturi R. Varadarajan Annual European Symposium on Algorithms, ESA 2019 pp. 12:1–12:14
- Brief Announcement: Connectivity Lower Bounds in Broadcast Congested Clique Shreyas Pai and Sriram V. Pemmaraju ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, PODC 2019 pp. 256–258
- Large-Scale Distributed Algorithms for Facility Location with Outliers
 Tanmay Inamdar, Shreyas Pai, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju
 International Conference on Principles of Distributed Systems, OPODIS 2018 pp. 5:1–5:16
- 13. Near-Optimal Clustering in the k-machine model Sayan Bandyapadhyay, Tanmay Inamdar, Shreyas Pai, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju ACM International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking, ICDCN 2018 pp. 15:1–15:10
- 14. Symmetry Breaking in the CONGEST Model: Time- and Message-Efficient Algorithms for Ruling Sets
 Shreyas Pai, Gopal Pandurangan, Sriram V. Pemmaraju, Talal Riaz, and Peter Robinson

International Symposium on Distributed Computing, DISC 2017 pp. 38:1–38:16

15. Brief Announcement: Symmetry Breaking in the CONGEST Model: Time- and Message-Efficient Algorithms for Ruling Sets Shreyas Pai, Gopal Pandurangan, Sriram V. Pemmaraju, Talal Riaz, and Peter Robinson ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, PODC 2017 pp. 207–209

Journal Publications

 Risk-aware temporal cascade reconstruction to detect asymptomatic cases Hankyu Jang, Shreyas Pai, Bijaya Adhikari, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju Knowledge and Information Systems 2022 pp. 3373–3399 2. Near-optimal clustering in the k-machine model Sayan Bandyapadhyay, Tanmay Inamdar, Shreyas Pai, and Sriram V. Pemmaraju Theoretical Computer Science 2022 pp. 80–97

Note: Conference Publications 4, 9, and Journal Publication 1 have authors in order of contribution, and all others have authors in alphabetical order of last name.

Fellowships

- ♦ Ballard Seashore Fellowship, Spring 2021
- ♦ Graduate College Summer Fellowship, Summer 2020 and 2019
- ♦ Graduate College Post Comprehensive Fellowship, Fall 2019

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

⋄ Instructor:

Algorithms (Spring 2017) (https://homepage.cs.uiowa.edu/~sriram/3330/spring17)

♦ Teaching Assistant:

Principles of Algorithmic Techniques (Fall 2021/2022),

Theory of Computation (Spring 2020),

Computer Science 1: Fundamentals (Fall 2016)

Invited Talks

♦ Algorithmic Lovasz Local Lemma

Guest Lecture at Program in Algorithmic and Combinatorial Thinking July 2021

- \diamond Sample-And-Gather: Fast Ruling Set Algorithms in the Low-Memory MPC Model Talk at $Helsinki\ Theory\ Seminar\ October\ 2020$
- ♦ Introduction to Distributed Algorithms (MIS and 3-Coloring Directed Rooted Trees) Guest Lectures at *Program in Algorithmic and Combinatorial Thinking* July 2017

SUMMER ACTIVITIES

- Research Internship at Technion Israel Institute of Technology, Haifa Host: Keren Censor-Hillel.
- May July 2019

- A Rosserch Internship at Indian Institu
- $\diamond~$ Research Internship at $\mathit{Indian~Institute~of~Science},$ Bangalore
- May July 2016

- Host: Siddharth Barman
- ⋄ Program in Algorithmic and Combinatorial Thinking at Princeton University June Aug 2015 Focus: Machine Learning
- ♦ Program in Algorithmic and Combinatorial Thinking at *Princeton University* June Aug 2014 Focus: Randomized Algorithms

ACADEMIC SERVICE

⋄ Conference Reviewer:

ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA).

ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing (PODC).

ACM Symposium on Parallelism in Algorithms and Architecture (SPAA).

International Symposium on Distributed Computing (DISC).

International Symposium on Stabilization, Safety, and Security of Distributed Systems (SSS).

Foundations of Software Technology and Theoretical Computer Science (FSTTCS).

International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking (ICDCN).

International Colloquium on Structural Information and Communication Complexity (SIROCCO). Conference on Principles of Distributed Systems (OPODIS).

⋄ Journal Reviewer:

Distributed Computing (DIST).

Theoretical Computer Science (TCS).

Journal of Parallel and Distributed Computing (JPDC).

⋄ Program Committee Member:

International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking (ICDCN) 2022. International Conference on Distributed Computing and Intelligent Technology (ICDCIT) 2023

♦ Other:

Co-Organizer for 1st Workshop on Algorithms for Massive Graphs (AMG) in DISC 2022 Co-Organizer for Meet other Postdocs and Students (MoPS) in DISC 2020 and 2021